A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare Interests - Youth, Series R FA327
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare Interests - Youth, Series R
1897-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
China Medical Board (U.S)
Spelman Fund
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Rockefeller family
Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial
Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
Spelman family
Rockefeller, John D.
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Rockefeller, David
Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller Foundation
Sealantic Fund, New York
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.)
Standard Oil Company
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
Davison Fund
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller, Winthrop
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
International Education Board
FA327
47 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research except where particular restrictions are noted.
Material in the Rockefeller family collections which provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net worth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr. C Business Interests D Civic Interests E Cultural Interests F Economic Reform Interests G Educational Interests H Friends and Services I Homes J Housing Interests K Medical Interests L Real Estate M Maps and Memorabilia N Religious Interests O Rockefeller Boards P Welfare - General Files Q World Affairs R Welfare - Youth Files S Documents T Public Relations U Public Land Law Review Commission V Greenrock W Properties X Costume Collection Y Media Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Scope and Contents note
This series contains 47 boxes of documents covering the years 1897-1961. This is a companion series to the Welfare General material and reflects the interest of the Rockefeller family, in particular John D. Rockefeller, Jr., and John D. Rockefeller 3rd, with issues and organizations specifically focused on American youth. The involvement of Mr. Rockefeller with the Young Mens Christian Association (YMCA) and Young Womens Christian Association (YWCA) dominates this series, accounting for 27 of the 47 boxes. The preponderance of material on these two organizations reflects both Mr. Rockefeller's strong Christian background and his choice of these agencies as the philanthropic vehicle for a variety of activities -- missionary outreach, settlement work, sex education lectures, urban recreation, and the Training Camp activities during the First World War. However, most of the material in this series describes the support given to local "Y's" in the United States and abroad. The strong interest of Laurance S. Rockefeller and Mary French Rockefeller in the work of the YMCA and YWCA is evident from these documents.
The next largest block of material, seven boxes in all, concerns John D. Rockefeller 3rd's work with American Youth Hostels. This organization sponsored youth tours in the United States and Europe combined with inexpensive accommodations. Mr. Rockefeller served as president of the organization for a number of years during the late 1940s and early 1950s. These files contain much information on the administrative, financial, and programmatic aspects of the operation.
The remainder of the material in the Welfare Youth Series is distributed across a variety of organizations in the child welfare and youth fields. There are sections on office involvement with the Boy Scouts, Girl Scouts, Big Brothers, Children's Village, and the Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies. The interest of other family members, particularly in the cousins generation, is also included.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Charities; Charities -- Investments; Child welfare; Civic improvement; Business enterprises, Foreign; Capital investments; Charitable contributions; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; International relations -- United States; Juvenile delinquency; Maternal health services; Medical care; International cooperation; International economic relations; International education; International relations; Parks -- New York (State); New York (State); Performing arts; Medical research; Medical education; New York (N.Y.); Medical sciences; Public health; Prohibition; Public policy; Public health administration; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; United States; Travel; Urban renewal; Urban policy; World War II; World War I; Public relations; Housing rehabilitation; Religion; Public welfare; Restoration and conservation; Religious institutions; State governments -- United States; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; Education; Education -- United States; Family planning; Federal government -- United States; Folk art; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Health insurance; Business; Arts; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art, Modern; Art; Economic development; Economic policy; Economics; Philanthropy; Philanthropy -- United States; Mauze, Abby Rockefeller; China Medical Board (U.S); Spelman Fund; Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich; Rockefeller family; Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Spelman family; Rockefeller, John D.; Rockefeller Center; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Rockefeller, David; Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller Foundation; Sealantic Fund, New York; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Standard Oil Company; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Davison Fund; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller, Winthrop; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth); Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman; International Education Board; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- )
- Boy Scouts of America
  - Boys Scouts of America, 1910-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. wrote article for magazine. Appeals for participation and contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, Thomas B. Appleget, James West.
    File Plan note
    12
  - Boys Scouts of America, 1918-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Boys Scouts of America, 1942-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boys Scouts of America, 1951-1961 (Box 1, Folder 0003A)
  - Boys Scouts of America - Boys' Life Magazine, 1923-1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. loan of $100,000 to magazine; information regarding loan and magazine activities.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Paterson Council, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Material regarding Communist activity among youth; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution to Council.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Adirondack Council, 1946-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller contributions.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Pocantico Hills Troop, 1938-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions and permission to use estate lands.
  - Boys Scouts of America - $10,000,000 Fund, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined request to contribute toward permanent reserve fund; advisors' attitudes regarding personnel policies in such organizations; communist youth organization rebuttals of the Boy Scouts. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, Raymond B. Fosdick.
  - Boys Scouts of America - $10,000,000 Fund - Revolving Fund, 1921-1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    $500,000 fund not related to later $10,000,000 drive; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $34,000; Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial gave $100,000.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Contributions, 1954-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Contributions to councils in Maine, Westchester, Fishers Island, and to International Council. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Contributions, 1954-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10A)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Contributions - Maine Council, 1926-1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. interest in and contributions to council; contributions by David Rockefeller and Nelson A. Rockefeller.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Contributions - Maine Council, 1926-1957 (Box 1, Folder 0011A)
  - Boys Scouts of America - Inter-Racial Service, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Descriptions of programs. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard.
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also Box 46, Folder 507.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Inter-Racial Service Contributions, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd contributions toward Negro scouting work in the South.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Greater New York Councils, 1919-1927 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Formerly called Foundation of New York. Rockefeller contributions; $50,000 pledge for camps, 1927; Frederick Kernachan Memorial. Invitations to serve on boards. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, David Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Greater New York Councils, 1927-1938 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Formerly called Foundation of New York. Rockefeller contributions; $50,000 pledge for camps, 1927; Frederick Kernachan Memorial. Invitations to serve on boards. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Greater New York Councils, 1939-1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Boys Scouts of America - Greater New York Councils, 1939-1957 (Box 2, Folder 0016A)
  - Boys Scouts of America - Greater New York Councils, 1957-1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Boys Scouts of America - Greater New York Councils - Contributions, 1937-1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $1,000 annually; smaller gifts by sons; special gifts.
  - Boys Scouts of America - Greater New York Councils - Contributions, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Boys Scouts of America - Hendrick Hudson Council
    Name later changed to Washington Irving Council. Contributions; office studies of Boy Scout movement. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    - Boys Scouts of America - Hendrick Hudson Council, 1920-1934 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Boys Scouts of America - Hendrick Hudson Council, 1934-1948 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Boys Scouts of America - Hendrick Hudson Council, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Boys Scouts of America - Hendrick Hudson Council, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 0022A)
    - Boys Scouts of America - Hendrick Hudson Council, 1955-1959 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Boys Scouts of America - Hendrick Hudson Council, 1955-1959 (Box 3, Folder 0023A)
  - Boys Scouts of America - Lakewood and Monmouth Council, 1927-1938 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Small annual gift by John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; final gift of $1,000 by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in 1937. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    See also Box 46, Folder 508.
  - Boy Scouts of America, 1923-1955 (Box 45, Folder 499)
  - Boy Scouts of America - Interracial Service, 1945-1946 (Box 46, Folder 507)
    Map of Local Councils, Boy Scouts of America, Rural Scouting Service, April 23, 1943.
  - Boy Scouts of America - Lakewood and Monmouth Council, 1927-1938 (Box 46, Folder 508)
    Monmouth Boy Scout Council Silver Anniversary Fund, Campaign Flyer Picture of John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and boys in front, 1935.
- Girls Scouts of America
  - Girl Scouts of America, 1917-1961 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s hope that Girl Scouts and Camp Fire Girls would be united. 1929 gift, $250,000 toward national program; appeals for contributions and participation. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    12.2
  - Girl Scouts of America, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 0025A)
  - Girl Scouts of America - Contributions, 1919-1954 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions to National and International Councils.
  - Girl Scouts of America - Greater New York Council, 1930-1938 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Formerly called Girl Scout Federation of Greater New York; handled financing for all boroughs. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions; smaller contributions by other members of family.
  - Girl Scouts of America - Greater New York Council, 1939-1959 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Girl Scouts of America - Greater New York Council - Contributions, 1949-1955 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Girl Scouts of America - Greater New York Council - Contributions, 1955-1961 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Girl Scouts of America - Greater New York Council - Contributions, 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 30A)
  - Girl Scouts of America - Greater New York Council - Manhattan Council, 1918-1936 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson.
  - Girl Scouts of America - Greater New York Council - Colored Work in Harlem, 1928-1932 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions; reports on activities.
  - Girl Scouts of America - Westchester County, 1924-1933 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions; Abby Aldrich Rockefeller a member of Council; Martha Baird Rockefeller gift toward camp modernization. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., David Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Thomas B. Appleget, Dana S. Creel.
  - Girl Scouts of America - Westchester County, 1933-1961 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Girl Scouts of America - Westchester County, 1946-1957 (Box 4, Folder 0034A)
  - Girl Scouts of America - Westchester County - Pocantico Hills Camp, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Girl Scout use of estate.
  - Girl Scouts of America, 1939-1959 (Box 45, Folder 500)
- Boy Rangers of America
  - Boy Rangers of America, 1938-1950 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    All appeals declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    12.3
- Camp Fire Girls
  - Camp Fire Girls, 1914-1927 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, David Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    13
  - Camp Fire Girls, 1927-1957 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Camp Fire Girls, 1941-1957 (Box 4, Folder 0038A)
- Girls' Service League of America
  - Girls' Service League of America, 1910-1931 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Began as New York Probation Association caring for wayward girls; operated Waverly House. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. annual contributions; Mary French Rockefeller contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Maude Miner.
    121
  - Girls' Service League of America, 1932-1961 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Girls' Service League of America, 1937-1961 (Box 4, Folder 40A)
- Women's Hotel Company
  - Women's Hotel Company, 1898-1918 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. subscribed $30,000 to stock of hotel for single women; no participation in management. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates.
- Playground and Recreation Associations
  - Playground and Recreation Associations - National Recreation Association, 1908-1951 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    Reports on activities; contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas B. Appleget, Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    122
  - Playground and Recreation Associations - National Recreation Association, 1939-1945 (Box 5, Folder 0042A)
  - Playground and Recreation Associations - National Recreation Association, 1952-1960 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    Reports on activities; contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas B. Appleget, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Playground and Recreation Associations - National Recreation Association, 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Playground and Recreation Associations - Play Schools Association, Inc., 1909-1920 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    Also includes Park and Playground Association of New York City material. Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Dana S. Creel, Mary French Rockefeller.
    121.2
  - Playground and Recreation Associations - Play Schools Association, Inc., 1920-1961 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Playground and Recreation Associations - Play Schools Association, Inc., 1952 (Box 5, Folder 0046A)
- Child Welfare
  - Child Welfare - Child Welfare Societies, 1924-1955 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    Appeals for contributions to a variety of child welfare organizations - most declined or ignored; a few scattered small gifts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Beardsley Ruml, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Mary French Rockefeller.
    140
  - Child Welfare - Child Welfare Societies, 1924-1955 (Box 5, Folder 0047A)
    Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Child Welfare - Child Welfare Societies, 1955-1958 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Child Welfare - Child Welfare Societies, 1955-1958 (Box 6, Folder 48A)
  - Child Welfare - Child Welfare Societies, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    Appeals for contributions to a variety of child welfare organizations - most declined or ignored; a few scattered small gifts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Beardsley Ruml, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Mary French Rockefeller, David Rockefeller.
  - Child Welfare - Child Welfare Societies, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 49A)
  - Child Welfare - Child Welfare Societies, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Child Welfare - Child Welfare Societies, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 51)